<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letters, at the instance of Sir George McKenzie of Rosebaugh, his Majesties advocat for his highness interest: and also at the instant of Sir William Paterson ... Sir Alexander Gibson ... and George McKenzie one of the clerks of exchequer ... and for the use of the creditors of the late Earl of Argile, and late Marquess of Argile his father ... against the creditors of the saids late Earl and late Marquess, and all vassals, and others having ... interest to the fortune and estate of the said late Earl, which fell in his Majesties hand, by sentence of forefalture underwritten.</title>
            <author>Scotland. Sovereign (1649-1685 : Charles II)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B05381</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52615064</idno>
  <idno type="VID">176169</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240877209</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1509C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R183072</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">52615064</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B05381)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176169)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2762:36)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Letters, at the instance of Sir George McKenzie of Rosebaugh, his Majesties advocat for his highness interest: and also at the instant of Sir William Paterson ... Sir Alexander Gibson ... and George McKenzie one of the clerks of exchequer ... and for the use of the creditors of the late Earl of Argile, and late Marquess of Argile his father ... against the creditors of the saids late Earl and late Marquess, and all vassals, and others having ... interest to the fortune and estate of the said late Earl, which fell in his Majesties hand, by sentence of forefalture underwritten.</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Sovereign (1649-1685 : Charles II)</author>
                  <author>Charles II, King of England, 1630-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the heir of Andrew Anderson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title vignette: Royal seal with initials C R.</note>
                  <note>Initial letter.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Argyll, Archibald Campbell, --  Marquis of, 1598-1661.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Argyll, Archibald Campbell, --  Earl of, 1629-1685.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Debtor and creditor --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Assignments for benefit of creditors --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176169:1"/>
            <p>LETTERS, At the Instance of Sir <hi>GEORGE McKENZIE</hi> of <hi>Rosebaugh,</hi> His <hi>Majesties</hi> Advocat for <hi>His Highness</hi> Interest: And also at the Instance of Sir <hi>WILLIAM PATERSON,</hi> one of the Clerks to His <hi>Majesties</hi> Privy Council: Sir <hi>ALEXANDER GIBSON</hi> of <hi>Adinstoun,</hi> one of the Clerks of Session: and <hi>GEORGE M<seg rend="sup">c</seg>KENZIE</hi> one of the Clerks of Exchequer, as Trusties, in Name, and for the use of the Creditors of the late Earl of <hi>Argile,</hi> and late Marquess of <hi>Argile</hi> his Father, to the effect after-specified.</p>
            <p>Against The Creditors of the saids late Earl and late Marquess, and all Vassals, and others having, or pretending to have Interest to the Fortune and Estate of the said late Earl, which fell in His <hi>Majesties</hi> hand, by Sentence of Forefalture underwritten.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINBƲRGH,</hi> Printed by the Heir of <hi>Andrew Anderson,</hi> Printer to His most Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majesty, anno <hi>DOM.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:176169:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:176169:2"/>
            <head>LETTERS, At the Instance of <hi>Sir</hi> GEORGE M<seg rend="sup">c</seg>KENZIE <hi>of</hi> Rosehaugh, <hi>His</hi> Majesties <hi>Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat for His Highness Interest: and also at the Instance of Sir</hi> WIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAM PATERSON, <hi>one of the Clerks to His</hi> Majesties <hi>Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil: Sir</hi> ALEXANDER GIBSON of <hi>Adinstoun, one of the Clerks of Session: and</hi> GEORGE M<seg rend="sup">c</seg>KENZIE, <hi>one of the Clerks of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, as Trusties, in Name of, and for the use of the Creditors of the late Earl of</hi> Argile, <hi>and late Marquess of</hi> Argile <hi>his Father, to the effect after-specified.</hi> AGAINST <hi>The Creditors of the saids late Earl and late Marquess, and all Vassals, and others having, or pretending to have Interest to the Fortune and Estate of the said late Earl, which fell in His</hi> Majesties <hi>hands, by Sentence of Forefalture under-written.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HARLES,</hi> by the grace of GOD, King of <hi>Great-Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of the Faith; To our Lovits,</p>
            <p>Messengers, Our Sheriffs in that part, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctly and severally, speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally constitute Greeting: For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asmuch as We by Our Charter under Our Great Seal of this ancient Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> of the date at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> the ninteenth day of <hi>May</hi> last by past, one thousand six hundred eighty and two years, Bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, That forasmuch as We considering, that <hi>Archibald</hi> late Earl of <hi>Argile</hi> being forefaulted upon a Process of Treason, before the Justice Court, the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> day of <hi>December</hi> last, And We being resolved to give an evident and undenyable proof of Our Justice to, and care of Our people, in preferring of the Creditors of the Family of <hi>Argile</hi> to Our Self, as well those who were Creditors to the late Marquess, as those who are Creditors to the late Earl, and of Our innat and Princely Clemency, in leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:176169:3"/>still a subsistence for the Family: Therefore We for Our Self and Our Successors, and as King and Prince of <hi>Scotland,</hi> Wills, and Declares in the first place, That the Jurisdictions, Offices, Superiorities, Constab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>laries, Patronages, and others after-specified, shall for ever be consolidated, and remain with Our Crown (as being necessary for the just support of Our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and too dangerous, both for Us and Our People, to be Heritable in the hand of any of Our Subjects, and We never having designed to Dispone the same) <hi>viz.</hi> The Offices of the Justice-Generalship of all the Islands of Our ancient King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> except <hi>Orknay</hi> and <hi>Zetland;</hi> the Justice-General<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of the Shires of <hi>Argile</hi> and <hi>Tarbot,</hi> and of all the remanent Lands and Estate belonging to the Earl of <hi>Argile,</hi> in Our said Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> the Heritable Life-tenendry of <hi>Argile</hi> and <hi>Tarbot-shire,</hi> the Heritable Chamberlandrie of both these Shires, the Office of Our Master-Houshold within our said Kingdom, the Heritable Sheriffship of <hi>Argile</hi> and <hi>Tarbot-shire,</hi> the Heritable Crownership, and Toshdorich or Mairship in these Shires: As also that half of the Casualities belonging to Us and Prince, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly Disponed by Us and Our Predecessors, to the Earl of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gile</hi> and his Predecessors, <hi>viz.</hi> The half of the Wards, Reliefs, Marriages, Non-entries, Escheats, Amersiaments, and of all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sualities whatsomever, belonging to Us and Prince, within the said Shires: And sicklike, the Patronage of all Kirks and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandries, which any manner of way did belong to the said late Earl and his Predecessors: And in like manner, the Constabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laries of the Castles of <hi>Craig, Neish, Tarbot, Carrick, Dunine, Swine,</hi> and <hi>Dunstaffuage,</hi> with the Profites, Rents, and Emoluments be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing thereto: As also the Superiorities of all and whatsome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Lands belonging to the Lord <hi>Lovit, John Mcclood</hi> of <hi>Haries,</hi> the Heirs of the late Lord <hi>Mcdonald,</hi>
               <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Mcdonald</hi> of <hi>Moidart,</hi> the Laird of <hi>M<seg rend="sup">c</seg>cleane,</hi> or any other Heritor of the name of <hi>Mcclean,</hi> the Laird of <hi>Lochzeal,</hi> the Laird of <hi>Calder,</hi> the Laird of <hi>Breackine,</hi> the Laird of <hi>Auchinbraick,</hi> the Laird of <hi>M<seg rend="sup">c</seg>naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toun,</hi> the Laird of <hi>Ardkindlayes,</hi>
               <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>M<seg rend="sup">c</seg>alister</hi> of <hi>Tarbot,</hi> the Laird of <hi>Laures,</hi> the Laird of <hi>Ardbrockel,</hi>
               <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Camp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel</hi> of <hi>Lundie,</hi>
               <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Campbel</hi> of <hi>Ardchattoun,</hi> the Laird of <hi>Ormsay,</hi> the Laird of <hi>Lochnel:</hi> As likewise the Superiority of the Burgh and House of <hi>Inverarioch</hi> and</p>
            <p>And in the next place, We for Our Selves and Our Successors, by Our Gift, under Our Great Seal afterspecified, Have Given, Granted and Disponed, to <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>M<seg rend="sup">c</seg>clean</hi> of <hi>Dochart,</hi> his Heirs-male, Successors and Assigneys whatsomever, as much Lands in <hi>Mull, Moorburn,</hi> not including <hi>Brolis,</hi> at the determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Our Commissioners after specified, as will pay an year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Rent, of the sum of five hundred pounds Sterling, free of all Ground Debts and Burdens, to be holden of Us and Our Succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors, conform to the Original Infestments of the saids Lands, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:176169:3"/>with the Castle of <hi>Dovat:</hi> as also <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Mcdougal</hi> of <hi>Lorn,</hi> his Heirs-male and Successors, as much Lands next ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent to the Castle of <hi>Dunolich,</hi> as will amount to eighteen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Merks yearly, to be designed by Our saids Commissioners, in manner foresaid, and sicklike to the Laird of <hi>M<seg rend="sup">c</seg>naughtoun,</hi> his Heirs-male, Successors and Assigneys, the Lands and <hi>Forrestrie</hi> of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> as the same were formerly pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest by him; and sicklike to <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>M<seg rend="sup">c</seg>donald</hi> of <hi>Glengai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> the Lands of <hi>Glengairy Knoydart</hi> and others Comprised or Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged from the deceast <hi>Eneas,</hi> Lord <hi>M<seg rend="sup">c</seg>donald,</hi> by the said <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chibald</hi> late Earl of <hi>Argile;</hi> which Debts and Rights following thereupon, We by Our said Charter, have Disponed in favours of the said. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>M<seg rend="sup">c</seg>donald</hi> of <hi>Glengairy,</hi> his Heirs and Assig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys, for now and ever: and in like manner, to <hi>Donald Mcdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nald</hi> of <hi>Moidart,</hi> all Heritable Right which the said <hi>Archibald</hi> late Earl of <hi>Argile,</hi> had upon his Lands and Estate, which We by Our said Charter, under Our Great Seal, of the date above and after exprest, have renounced in favours of the said <hi>Donald Mcdonald,</hi> his Heirs and Assigneys, dispensing with the generality foresaid, and admitting the samine to be as sufficient, as if every particular Debt above-mentioned, Right and Diligence following there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, were at length specified in the said Charter, whereanent We have Dispensed for ever. Likeas, We out of Our Princely Goodness and Bounty, by Our said Charter aforesaid, have Giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, Granted and Disponed, Heretably and Irredeemably, to <hi>John Campbel,</hi> second Son to the said <hi>Archibald</hi> late Earl of <hi>Argile,</hi> his Heirs-male, Successors and Assigneys whatsomever, as much Land out of the said Estate of <hi>Argile,</hi> as will extend to the sum of two hundred pound Serling Money, of yearly real Rent, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to the Rental of the said Estate of <hi>Argile,</hi> to be Designed, Allocat and appointed to him by Our saids Commissioners: and to <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Campbel,</hi> third Son to the said <hi>Archibald</hi> late Earl of <hi>Argile,</hi> his Heirs-Male, Successors and Assigneys whatsom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, as much Land out of the said Estate of <hi>Argile,</hi> and that He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably and Irredeemably, as will amount to the sum of an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fifty pound Sterling Money, of yearly Rent, conform to the Rental of the said Estate of <hi>Argile,</hi> to be Designed, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locat and appointed, to the said <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Campbel</hi> and his foresaids, by Our saids Commissioners: and sicklike to <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Campbel,</hi> fourth Son to the said <hi>Arhibald</hi> late Earl of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gile,</hi> his Heirs-male, Successors and Assigneys whatsomever, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably and Irredeemably, as much Land out of the said Estate of <hi>Argile,</hi> as will Extend in yearly Rent to the sum of an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fifty pound Sterling yearly, conform to the Rental of the said Estate of <hi>Argile,</hi> to be Designed, allocat and appointed to him and his forsaids, by Our saids Commissioners after exprest: Likeas, We out of Our said bounty and goodness, by Our said Charter, have Given, Granted and Disponed to Lady <hi>Ann
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:176169:4"/>Campbell</hi> eldest lawful Daughter to the said <hi>Archibald,</hi> late Earl of <hi>Argyle,</hi> now Spouse to <hi>Richard Maitland</hi> of <hi>Didope</hi> Our Justice Clerk of Our said Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> her Heirs Male succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors or Assigneys whatsomever: Asmuch Land out of the said Estate of <hi>Argyle</hi> as will extend to, and be worth in yearly Rent conform to the forsaid Rental, The sum of one hundreth pound Sterling Yearly to be designed and appointed to her and her forsaids, be Our saids Commissioners. And lastly, to Lady <hi>Jean Campbel,</hi> second Daughter to the said <hi>Archibald</hi> late Earl of <hi>Argyle,</hi> asmuch Land out of the said Estate of <hi>Argyle,</hi> and that Heritably and Irredeemablie, to her Heirs Male, Successors and Assigneys whatsomever, as will be worth and extend in yearly Rent, conform to the Rental of the said Estate of <hi>Argyle:</hi> to the sum of an hundred pounds money forsaid, yearly to be designed, allocat, and appointed to her and her forsaids be Our said Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners, in manner above and after-mentioned: And that in full Contentation payment and Satisfaction to the said Children of the said <hi>Archibald,</hi> late Earl of <hi>Argyle,</hi> of all Bonds of Provision, or Contracts; and of all other sums of Money resting to them be their said Father. And also We, by Our said Charter, have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served to <hi>Archibald</hi> late Lord <hi>Lorn,</hi> the Lands wherein he and his Lady stands confirmed: As likewise, We, with advice and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of Our trusty Cusings and Counsellors <hi>John</hi> Duke of <hi>Lauderdail,</hi> President of Our Privy Council of this Our ancient Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi>
               <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> Marquess of <hi>Athol</hi> Lord Privy Seal, <hi>Alexander</hi> Earl of <hi>Murray</hi> sole Secretar of State, <hi>William</hi> Earle of <hi>Queensberry,</hi> and <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> Earl of <hi>Strathmoor;</hi> as also with consent of Our trustie Counsellor <hi>Charles Maitland</hi> of <hi>Haltoun,</hi> Our Thesaurer Deput of Our said Kingdom, Our Commissioners for the Thesaurie, Comptrolers and Thesaurie of new Augmentations, and with the advice and consent of the remanent Lords of the Exchequer of Our said Kingdom, have by Our said Charter under Our great Seal, of the date abovewritten, given, granted and disponed, and for Us, and Our Successors, with advice and consent forsaid per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually confirmed to Sir <hi>Alexander Gibson</hi> one of Our Clerks to the Session, Sir <hi>William Paterson</hi> Clerk to Our Privy Council, and <hi>George M<seg rend="sup">c</seg>kenzie</hi> one of Our Clerks to the Exchequer, as trusties for the use and behove after exprest allenarlie; and fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of either of them be decease, to the surviver with and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the exception of the Jurisdictions, Offices, Superiorities, Constabularies, Patronages, Lands and others above-specified: All and haill the Earldoms, Lordships, Barronies, Tennendries and others above-mentioned, which pertained and belonged of before to the late Earl of <hi>Argyle,</hi> and are now fallen in Our hand, by the Forefalture forsaid, <hi>viz.</hi> All and sundrie the Lands and Barrony of <hi>Lochane,</hi> the Lands of <hi>Ardfoludnes, Glen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yra, Glenshira,</hi> and <hi>Latter</hi> within the forsaid Barronie, the Lands and Barrony of <hi>Glenorchie,</hi> all and hail the Lands and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:176169:4"/>Lordship of <hi>Cowall,</hi> with the Forth of <hi>Bemore,</hi> pertaining and belonging thereto; with all and sundry Castles, Maner-places, Milnes, Woods, Fishings, Forrests, Sheillings, Grassings, Fish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Teynds, Houses, Biggings and Pertinents of the samen; all and hail the Lands and Barrony of <hi>Overciual,</hi> the Lands of <hi>Straquhare,</hi> extending to fiftie one merks and a half merk land of old extent: The Lands of <hi>Straitheathin, Gleninassin, Glenlean, Lochstravin, Shed, Arrinslat</hi> toward <hi>Fleeming, Invernil,</hi>and <hi>Clackkan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, Auchatachevin,</hi> the Lands of <hi>Ardmeinnock, Lyseaga, Darnagerchmore, Glentire</hi> and <hi>Darnagevochbeg,</hi> the lands and Barrony of <hi>Otterwerin,</hi> the lands of <hi>Glessary, Ederline,</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written, <hi>viz.</hi> The lands of <hi>Minart,</hi> and <hi>Kilmochallbeg, Gorthan, Ring, Nockness, Artcastles, Callochie, Auchinbreck, Belmoir, Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitchail, Hozinan, Monenenarath, Knockallaway, Fewling, Tuyne. Garivalt, Craigneuar, Thanganalith, Earquhill, Tornblairne, Lagg, Auchtine, Chirlich, Craigmurthill,</hi> all and hail the lands of <hi>Craig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neish, Melfart,</hi> with the Castles, Towers, Maner-places, Isles, Loches, Fishings, Salmond-fishings, and other Fishings and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinents of the samen lyand within the Shireffdome of <hi>Argyle.</hi> All and hail the Lands and Barronie of <hi>Tarbot,</hi> with the Castles, Towers and maner Places of the samen, and hail parts and pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicles thereof, lyand within the Shiriffdome of <hi>Tarbot</hi> of old, and now within the said Sheriffdoom of <hi>Argyle,</hi> as also, all and sundry the Lands, Lordship and Barrony of <hi>Lorn,</hi> the said Lands of <hi>Longtoirs, Shiunay, Sheill, Corsseraw,</hi> and <hi>Leissmoir;</hi> within the forsaid, Lordships, Lands and Barrony of <hi>Killmoon,</hi> the Lands of <hi>Beadland,</hi> all and sundry the saids Lands and Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rony of <hi>Killmichael,</hi> the Lands and Barrony of <hi>Skipnet,</hi> lyand of old within the Shiriffdome of <hi>Tarbot,</hi> and now within the Shirif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Argyle.</hi> All and hail the five merk Land of old extent of <hi>Annan</hi> with the Fishings of the samen upon the water of <hi>Ave,</hi> and pertinents thereof, and the one merk Land of old extent of <hi>Auchindean,</hi> lyand within the Barrony of <hi>Lothow,</hi> and Shirifdome of <hi>Argyle</hi> forsaid, with the Castles, Towres, Fortalices, Isles, Loches, Fishings, Forrests, Parts, Pendicles, and Pertinents of the samine with the Teinds, Personage and Vicarage thereof, and Colledge Kirk of <hi>Killmoon;</hi> and the hail other Kirk Lands, Benefices, Chaplanries, Annexis, Connexis, Dependences; and Pertinences whatsomever, of all and fundrie the Lands, Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships, Barronies and others forsaid: All and sundrie the Lands and Barrony of Kirktoun of <hi>Inchmeir,</hi> with the Towres, Forta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lices and maner Place of the samen, with the Isles, Loches, Tennents, Tennendries, Annexis Connexis, Parts, Pendicles, thereof: all and hail the Lands and Barronie of <hi>Rossneath</hi> with the Towres, Fortifications, Houses, Biggings, Yeards, Orch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeards, Milnes, Milne-lands, Woods, Forrests, Isles, Loches, Fishings, Tennents, Tennendries, Annexis, Connexis, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinents lyand within the Shirifdome of <hi>Dumbartoun.</hi> All and sundrie the Lands of <hi>Innerquhapel</hi> in <hi>Glenfurd,</hi> the <hi>Toylet,</hi> all
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:176169:5"/>and sundrie the Lands of two <hi>Ardinblauches,</hi> and two <hi>Craig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ubilks,</hi> and half merk Land lyand within the territory of <hi>Inner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quhapel,</hi> and an merk Land of old possest be <hi>Jver Mckenzie.</hi> The Lands of <hi>Stuck</hi> and <hi>Blairbeg,</hi> the Lands of <hi>Ferrie,</hi> the Lands of <hi>Feirone</hi> with the Castles, Towres, manner Places, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rests, Parts, Pendicles, and Pertinents of the samen, with the Loches, Isles, Fishings, Tennents, Tennendries, Parts Pendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles and Pertinents whatsomever, of the said Lands, and others forsaids, lyand within the Shirifdome of <hi>Argyle:</hi> all and hail the twenty pound Land of <hi>Duzzie, vix.</hi> The seven merk land of <hi>Caule</hi> and <hi>Glensarachin;</hi> the seven merk land of <hi>Ardseal,</hi> and <hi>Lagnahall;</hi> the three merk land of <hi>Bellesheils,</hi> the five merk lands of <hi>Achanadaroch,</hi> the three merk land of <hi>Achliqhary,</hi> the five merk land of <hi>Anchquhary</hi> and <hi>Auchinblaun,</hi> all and hail the twenty merk land of <hi>Glenvain</hi> with the Castles, Towres, Forta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lices, maner Places, Houses, Biggings, Milnes, Multures, Woods, Forrests, Meadows, Banks, Loches, Fishings, Tennents, Tennen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dries, Annexis, Connexis, Parts, Pendicles and Pertinents whatsomever of the saids Lands, and others above-written, lyand within the said Shirefdome of <hi>Argyle.</hi> All and hail the Lands of <hi>Paunnells,</hi> the five merk Lands of <hi>Odullator,</hi> the Lands of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therglen,</hi> the Lands of <hi>Drumkean</hi> and <hi>Blairwevock</hi> with the Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, Fortalices, maner Places, Houses, Biggings, Yeards Orch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeards, Milnes, Woods, Fishings, Coalls, Coall-heughs, Forrests, Peats, Moures Meadows, Banks, Loches, Isles, Fishings, Parts, Pendicles and Pertinents thereof, lyand within the Shirifdome of <hi>Perth.</hi> All and hail the Lands of little <hi>Sauline,</hi> all and hail the Lands of <hi>Borland</hi> of <hi>Sauline,</hi> with Castles and Towres, Fortalices, Milnes, Mutltures, Woods, Banks, Loches Isles, Fishings, Annexis, Connexis, Parts, Pendicles and Pertinents thereof, lyand within the Shiriffdome of <hi>Fife.</hi> All and hail the Lands and Barrony of <hi>Menstry,</hi> lyand within the Shireffdome of <hi>Clackmannon,</hi> all and hail the Lands and Barrony of <hi>Bochon</hi> ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and within the Shiriffdome of <hi>Striviling,</hi> all and hail the Lands and Barrony of <hi>Ardnamurchow,</hi> wherein comprehending the Lands, Isles, Milnes, Woods, Fishings, and Fishings and others underwritten, <hi>viz.</hi> All and hail the Lands and Isles <hi>Colousay,</hi> comprehending the Lands, Milnes, Fishings, and others after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, <hi>viz.</hi> all and hail the two merk and half merk Land of <hi>Bellinhard:</hi> the five merk Land of the two <hi>Killiedranises,</hi> the two merk Land and half merk Land of the two <hi>Killhattums,</hi> the two merk and half merk land of <hi>Machenathoiss</hi> and <hi>Ballviers,</hi> the two merk and half merk Lands of <hi>Killrevey</hi> and <hi>Marchribeg,</hi> the two merk and half merk Lands of the two <hi>Vreskinshes,</hi> the two merk and half merk Lands of the two <hi>Ballarunches,</hi> the sexteen shilling and eight pennie Land of <hi>Skallisag</hi> with all and sundrie, Castles, Towres, maner Places, Houses, Biggings, Yeards, Orchyeards, Outsetts, Annexis, Connexis, Dependences Milnes, Milne-lands, Multures, Wood, Fisshings Meadows,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:176169:5"/>Bonds, Coals, Coal-heughs, Lochs, Isles, Tennents, Tennendries, Forrests, Parts, Pendicles and Pertinents whatsomever of the saids hail Lands, and others <hi>respective</hi> above-written, with the Perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents all and sundry the Lands of <hi>Arduamuchan,</hi> containing the particular Lands and others under-written, <hi>viz.</hi> all and hail the twenty shilling Land of <hi>Letter-lochshiel,</hi> the two merk and half merk Land of <hi>Acherkeils,</hi> the two merk and half merk Land of <hi>Langa,</hi> the two merk Land of <hi>Glenbervadail,</hi> the two merk Land of <hi>Glenbeg,</hi> the two merk and half merk Land of <hi>Glenmoir,</hi> the two merk and half merk Land of <hi>Ardsliggensh,</hi> the two mark and half merk Land of <hi>Camusnagle,</hi> the two merk and half merk Land of <hi>Tornamonth,</hi> the two merk and half merk Land of <hi>Borblaig,</hi> the two merk and half Land of <hi>Corniscilen,</hi> the two merk and half merk Land of <hi>Skenenth,</hi> the three merk and half merk Land of <hi>Mingair,</hi> the two merk Land of <hi>Killechlen,</hi> the two merk and half merk Land of <hi>Cunsagmore,</hi> the two merk Land of <hi>Auchnaquhis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,</hi> the twenty shilling Lands of <hi>Ormsagbig,</hi> the two merk Land of <hi>Ʋdine,</hi> the two merk and half merk Land of <hi>Auchinschaw,</hi> the two merks and half merk Land of <hi>Glendrien,</hi> the one merk Land of <hi>Pinchonich,</hi> the twenty shilling Land of <hi>Taskistle,</hi> the three merk Land of <hi>Auchave,</hi> the two merk Land of <hi>Branalt,</hi> the two merk and half merk Land of <hi>Killiemore,</hi> the two merk and half merk Land of <hi>Swardile-Corich,</hi> the two merk and half merk Land of <hi>Swardilemore,</hi> the two merk and half merk Land of <hi>Swardil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beg,</hi> the two merk and half merk Land of <hi>Orkeil,</hi> the one merk Land of <hi>Reynkaneth,</hi> the shilling eight pennie Land of <hi>Class,</hi> the six shilling eight pennie Land of <hi>Ardyna,</hi> two merk and half merk Land of <hi>Ardore,</hi> six shilling eight pennie Land of <hi>Locke,</hi> six shilling eight pennie Land of <hi>Langarie,</hi> six shilling eight pennie Land of <hi>Craiggow,</hi> and two merk Land of <hi>Ardipe,</hi> with all and sundry Castles, Towers, Fortalices, maner places, Lochs, Isles, Woods, Fishings, Annexis, Connexis, Dependences, Forrests, Parts, Pendicles and Pertinents of the samine whatsoever: And sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, all and hail the Isle <hi>Swinart</hi> containing the Lands and others underwritten, <hi>viz.</hi> all and hail the two merk and half merk Land of the two <hi>Ranaquhans,</hi> two merk and half merk Land of <hi>Cammissian;</hi> the three merk Land of <hi>Reshaple;</hi> the an merk Land of <hi>Tarbot,</hi> the ten shilling Land of <hi>Camanskeinish</hi> and <hi>Camstarsey;</hi> two merk and half merk Land of <hi>Polloch;</hi> the two merk and half merk Land of <hi>Ronaldmoir;</hi> two merk and half merk Land of <hi>Ard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nastank;</hi> two merk and half merk Land of <hi>Anchnahil;</hi> the two merk and half merk Land of <hi>Orrindile,</hi> two merk and half merk Land of <hi>Drumtorrin;</hi> two merk and half merk Land of <hi>Strontean;</hi> and two merk and half merk Land of <hi>Auchnileare;</hi> with all and sundrie Castles, Towers, Fortalices, maner places, Houses, Big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings, Milns, Woods, Forrests, Fishings, Lochs, Outsetts, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetts, Dependences, Parts, Pendicles, and Pertinents of the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine whatsomever, Lyand of old within the Sheriffdom of <hi>Inverness</hi> and <hi>Tarbot,</hi> and now within the Sheriffdom of <hi>Argile;</hi> all and hail
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:176169:6"/>the Lands and Barony of <hi>Balweil,</hi> comprehending the Lands and others underwritten, <hi>viz.</hi> all and hail the Isle of <hi>Cronsay,</hi> extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to five merk Land with the Pertinents; all and hail the six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen shilling Land and eight Pennie Land of <hi>Garvite</hi> in <hi>Collin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>say;</hi> all and hail the eight shilling Land in <hi>Strowin</hi> in <hi>Deura,</hi> with the hail Parts, pendicles and Pertinents thereof, lyand within the Sheriffdom of <hi>Argile,</hi> with the Teind-Sheaves and other Teinds, aswell parsonage as Viccarage great as small of the saids Lands and Isles <hi>respective:</hi> and sicklike, the just third part of all and hail the eighteen merk Land of <hi>Qeins; viz.</hi> all and hail the eighteen shilling Land of <hi>Torsay;</hi> eighteen shilling Land of <hi>Arigainathan;</hi> eighteen shilling Land of <hi>Auchindresh;</hi> eight shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Land of <hi>Wreoth;</hi> nine shilling Land of <hi>Derevey;</hi> and eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen shilling Land of <hi>Augintoun,</hi> with House, Biggings, Parts, Pendicles and Pertinents thereof, lyand in the Isle of <hi>Mull</hi> and within the said Sheriffdom of <hi>Tarbot</hi> of old, and now within the said Sheriffdom of <hi>Argile;</hi> as also, all and hail the Isle of <hi>Roune,</hi> extending to six merk Land of old extent; to wit, the four merk Land of <hi>Kilmoir;</hi> and two merk Land of <hi>Northag;</hi> with all and sundry Houses, Biggings, Fishings, Parts, Pendicles and Pertinents of the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, lyand within the Sheriffdom of <hi>Argile</hi> foresaid; all and hail the three merk Land, of old extent of <hi>Drumyne</hi> and <hi>Auchelmane,</hi> with House, Biggings, Parts, Pendicles, annexis, connexis and Pertinents thereof, lyand within the Lordship of <hi>Morverne;</hi> all and hail the Lands of <hi>Kilmachaiche, Gartnagairoch</hi> and <hi>Muthtrie,</hi> extending to eight merk Land, of old extent with all and sundrie Houses, Biggings, Yards, Orchards, Milns, Woods, Fishings, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendences, Profites, Commodities, Casualities, Parts, Pendicles and Pertinents of the samine, lyand within the Sheriffdom of <hi>Argile;</hi> as also, all and hail the Lands and others underwritten, <hi>viz.</hi> all and hail the sixteen shilling and eight penny Land of <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ecuisly,</hi> sixteen shilling and eight penny Land of <hi>Cambackrie;</hi> sixteen shilling and eight penny Land of <hi>Recunes;</hi> sixteen shilling eight pennie Land of <hi>Tarbot,</hi> all lyand within the Isle of <hi>Jura;</hi> sixteen shilling eight penny Land of <hi>Mulbouie,</hi> lyand within the Isle of <hi>Scarba;</hi> eight shilling and four penny Land of <hi>Garvallen</hi> and <hi>Donnechonnel,</hi> with the Isles of <hi>Glacheniver</hi> and <hi>Coulbrandin;</hi> six merk Land of <hi>Dousmoloch</hi> and <hi>Ranochane,</hi> lyand in the Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chine of <hi>Kilcamanel;</hi> four merk Land of <hi>auchmellan,</hi> lyand with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Parochine of <hi>Kilberry</hi> and Sheriffdom of <hi>Argile</hi> foresaid; all and hail the Lands of <hi>Balwel</hi> extending to five Merk Land, of old extent with the manner, Place, House, Biggings and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinents thereof; all and hail the Lands of <hi>Wardend,</hi> with the Wood of the samine, House, Biggings and Pertinents thereof; all and hail the Lands of <hi>Ballairds,</hi> over and nether, with the Miln thereof, Houses, Biggings, annexis, connexis and their Perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents, lyand by annexation within the Barony of <hi>Glenegies</hi> Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chine of <hi>Drumean,</hi> and Sheriffdom of <hi>Pearth;</hi> all and hail the Lands of <hi>Calemor,</hi> with the Pertinents, and <hi>Raslinglorne,</hi> with
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:176169:6"/>House, Biggings, Yards, Orchards and Pertinents of the samine, lyand within the Barony of <hi>Haddin</hi> and Sheriffdom of <hi>Pearth</hi> foresaid; all and hail the Lands of <hi>Kepd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urie</hi> and Pertinents of the samine, lyand in the Sheriffdom of <hi>Pearth</hi> foresaid; and all and hail the five m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rk Land of <hi>auchrig</hi> over and nether, lyand within the Sheriffdom of <hi>Pearth</hi> foresaid, with the Libertie and Priviledge of Mosse and Muire, to the saids Lands of <hi>auchrig,</hi> within the Lands of Letter and Barony of <hi>Roskie,</hi> according to use and wont; all and hail the fourty shilling Land and Forrestry of <hi>Benziemore,</hi> with Parts, Pendicles and Pertinents of the samine, lyand within the Sheriffdom of <hi>Pearth</hi> foresaid, all and hail the Lands and Barony of <hi>Eyge,</hi> comprehending the Lands, Baronies and others afterspecified, <hi>viz</hi> all and hail the Lands and Baronie of <hi>Lochyield</hi> therein comprehending the Lands and others under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written, <hi>viz.</hi> all and hail the Lands of <hi>Bamby, Meikeinith, Helin, Craiglong, Torpith, arnat, annachido, Kilmailie, auchmolig, Drum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraser, Molochsyne, Wor, Wallie, Hassa, Farna, Strone, Falliack, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beg, Auchtiloun, Kinloch, Drumlace, Coulie, Knappe, Machiacho, Clariothack, Musheroloch, Creive, Sallachan</hi> and half of <hi>Landallie,</hi> with all and sundrie Castles, Towers, manner Places, annexis, connexis, Parts, Pendicles and Pertinents of the samine, lyand within the Sheriffdom of <hi>Argile</hi> foresaid; all and hail the Lands of <hi>Inneramble, Frostblair, auchteramble, Goriasplace</hi> of <hi>Dalzeamble, Quarter, aulater</hi> and <hi>achanvie</hi> with the Pertinents, lyand within the Sheriffdom of <hi>Pearth;</hi> all and hail the Lands and Barony of <hi>arguar</hi> underwritten, <hi>viz.</hi> the one merk Land of <hi>Calpe</hi> and <hi>Garvan:</hi> the twenty shilling land of <hi>Diuskie:</hi> the one merk land of <hi>auchinpoble</hi> and <hi>Trensach;</hi> the one merk Land of <hi>Strongagaren</hi> and <hi>Chavelzelk</hi> the one merk Land of <hi>Blairbowie</hi> and <hi>Corsbeg,</hi> the one merk Land of the two <hi>Innerskalvilluillies;</hi> the one merk Land of <hi>Coulaplin</hi> and <hi>Cradalich;</hi> the one merk Land of <hi>archaulan</hi> and <hi>Auchnan;</hi> the one merk Land of <hi>Lednevis</hi> and <hi>Craigvaytan;</hi> the one merk Land of <hi>Nearachan</hi> and <hi>Lakeith;</hi> the twenty shilling Land of <hi>Dundoch</hi> and <hi>alehouse;</hi> the one merk Land of <hi>Kilbodin;</hi> two merk and ten shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Land of <hi>Coulie;</hi> twenty three shilling and four pennie Land of <hi>Sallachanbeg;</hi> two merk Land of <hi>Sallachinmoir;</hi> two merk of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nersandax, Innerbrachater;</hi> half merk Land of the two <hi>Breverkil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die</hi> and <hi>Clasamuck,</hi> extending in the hail to twenty two merk Lands, with Castles, Towers, Fortalices, manner Places, Houses, Biggings, Milns, Multures, Woods, Fishings, as well in salt as in fresh water, annexis, connexis, Woods Forrests, and all and sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry their Pertments whatsomever, lyand within the Sheriffdom of <hi>Argile</hi> foresaid; all and hail the Lands and Barony of <hi>Gyga,</hi> extending to twenty pound Land underwritten, <hi>vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> The Lands of <hi>Cameront, Tarbot, ardhay, ardglames, Chanteroch, Laint, Kilha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, ardvynes, Drumsmore, Drumgenbeg, Scoul</hi> and <hi>Duncro,</hi> with the Castles, Towers, Manner-Places annexis, connexis, Parts, Pendicles and Pertinents of the samine, lyand within the Sheriff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Argile</hi> foresaid; all and hail these sixteen merk Lands ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and in <hi>Kintire, viz. Macherichanis, Clathkill</hi> and <hi>Tradigall, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachino</hi> and <hi>Lestrauchin,</hi> with all and sundry Parts, Pendicles
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:176169:7"/>and Pertinents of the samine, lyand within the Sheriffdom of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gile;</hi> all and hail the lands and others underwritten, <hi>viz.</hi> all and hail the twenty four merk five shilling land of <hi>Arross</hi> in the Isle of <hi>Mull;</hi> the lands of <hi>Oskeambell;</hi> the lands of <hi>Corkamull;</hi> the lands of <hi>Fannanover</hi> in <hi>Leirwalleneil;</hi> all and hail the lands of <hi>Brollis,</hi> all and hail the eight merk land, lyand in <hi>Ardmenach;</hi> all lyand with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Isle of <hi>Mull;</hi> all and hail the lands of <hi>Mulbony,</hi> lyand in the Isle of <hi>Scarbay;</hi> all and hail the lands of <hi>Preag, Gnananagall, Gle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namuck, Ardscallanesh,</hi> and lands of Ardbignies, lyand in the Isle of Jura, with all and sundry Parts, Pendicles, Houses, Big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings, Woods, Forrests, Fishings and pertinents of the famine, lyand within the Sheriffdom of <hi>Argile</hi> foresaid, with the Teinds, Parso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage and Viccarage of the hail Paroch Kirk and Parochin of K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calmanel, and hail profits of the samine thereto belonging, lying within the Sheriffdom of Argile foresaid; and all and hxil the lands and others under-written, <hi>viz.</hi> all and hail the lands and Barony of Lundie, comprehending all and sundry the lands cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Mains of Lundy, alias West-Dronlaw; all and hail the lands of Pitterna, with the pertinents; all and hail the Kirktoun lands of Lundy, with the Loch thereof, and lands called Brae lands of Lundy, with the pertinents, with the Miln of Lundy, with the Miln-lands, Multures, Sequels and pertinents of the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, all and hail the lands of Easter-keith, with the Loch cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Lang-loch, and Fishings of the samine; all and hail the lands of Ladyet; the lands of Lady-reife and Argarth; all and hail the lands of Smeithtoun-nether; all and hail the lands of Balchaneo, with the Loch called the lands of Balchand, and Fishings of the famine; all and hail the lands of Pendrich, with the parts, pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicles and pertinents of the samine; all and hail the lands of Droan, with the Castles, Towers, Fortalices, manner places, Houses, Biggings, Tennents, Tennendries, annexis, connexis, parts, pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicles and pertinents of the said Barony of Lundy, lyand within the Sheriffdom of For<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar; all and hail the lands of Camneck, over <hi>Auchindeck,</hi> and nether <hi>Auchindeck,</hi> the lands of over <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick,</hi> nether <hi>Elreck, Doun, Dalnacabock, Kirktoun, Pilrochie,</hi> and <hi>Bellitsie, Dundounni,</hi> with the eight part of all and sundrie the lands of wester <hi>Inneraritie,</hi> all and hail the three third parts of easter <hi>Inneraritie,</hi> with the Milne, Milne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands and astrict Multures of the samen, all and hail the three third parts of all and sundrie the lands of <hi>Glenma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kie</hi> with the Parts, Pendicles, Annexis, Connexis and Pertinents of the samen, lyand within the Barrony of <hi>Glenylla,</hi> and Sherifdome of <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>far,</hi> all and hail that fourth part of the half of the Town of <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brogie,</hi> together with the other part thereof possest sometime by <hi>Jonet Allanson,</hi> and the fourth part of the half of the said Town sometime possest be <hi>Andrew Bell,</hi> lyand within the Shireffdome of <hi>Perth</hi> forsaid, all and hail the Lands and Barrony of <hi>Glenelg,</hi> with Castles, Towres, Fortalices, maner Places, Houses, Big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings, Yards, Orchards Milnes, Milne-lands, Multers, Woods,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:176169:7"/>Forrests, Fishings, and hail Pertinents of the samine whatsome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, lyand within the Sheriffdome of <hi>Innerness,</hi> all and hail the seven merk Land of <hi>Avishack,</hi> one merk Land of <hi>Eygk</hi> with the Pertinents, lyand within the Sheriffdome of <hi>Innerness,</hi> all and hail that three merk land of <hi>Moydart:</hi> all and hail that nine merk land lyand in the Islle of <hi>Eygk,</hi> comprehending the lands of <hi>Galmoscull, Saudie, Groulin,</hi> third part land of <hi>Clittill:</hi> Half land of <hi>Knock-daltack,</hi> and half of the land of <hi>Balmerich,</hi> the hail four one merk land of <hi>Morar,</hi> comprehending the town and lands outsetts aftermentioned, <hi>viz.</hi> All and hail the lands of <hi>Crosell,</hi> The lands of <hi>Gray:</hi> the lands of <hi>Drowassel,</hi> the lands of <hi>Ochaldell:</hi> the lands of <hi>Counchatter:</hi> the lands of <hi>Scamadeill:</hi> the lands of <hi>Fettielane:</hi> the lands of <hi>Feranrie:</hi> the lands of <hi>Dell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>athich:</hi> the lands of <hi>Inneresick:</hi> the land of <hi>Marieshell.</hi> the lands of <hi>Lochboir</hi> with both the sides of the Loch: the lands of <hi>North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baith, Arrichir,</hi> and <hi>Neckerfed:</hi> the lands of <hi>Pauliskinen:</hi> all and hail the seven merk land of <hi>Arsack,</hi> comprehending the lands of <hi>Kippack,</hi> with the old marches and bounds thereof: the lands of <hi>Mayne, Ardnapeul, Torabreich</hi> and <hi>Bonarray,</hi> all and hail the twenty three merks lands of <hi>Kindies:</hi> all and hail the six merks lands of <hi>Bowistil</hi> within the Isle of <hi>Northvenish</hi> with Castles, Towers, Fortalices, Manner-places, houses, Biggings, Yeards, Orchards, Milnes, Milne-lands, Multures, Woods, Forrests, Banks, Meadows, Fishings, alsewell in salt as in fresh waters, Tofts, Crofts and Pertinents of the samine, all and hail the twenty merk land of <hi>Frierchug:</hi> the twelve merk land of <hi>Bambecula,</hi> and one merk land of <hi>Gargrinens,</hi> with Castles, Towres, Fortalices, Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner-places, Houses, biggings, Yeards, Orchards, Milnes, Milne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, Multures, Woods, Forrests, Meadows, Banks, Islands, Lochs Fishings, Parts, Pendicles, and Pertinents of the samine whatsome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, lyand within the Island of <hi>Ʋnist,</hi> and Sheriffdome of <hi>Inver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> foresaid: all and hail the Lordship and Barrony of <hi>Kintire,</hi> comprehending all and sundrie the Land, Islands, Feu-farmes, and others particularly underwritten, <hi>viz.</hi> All and hail the lands and Lordship of <hi>Kintire,</hi> comprehending specially in themselves, all and sundrie the Lands and others underwritten, <hi>viz.</hi> The lands of <hi>Cannochan</hi> and <hi>Donnanultichie</hi> extending to twentie pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny land, the lands of <hi>Ochinross,</hi> extending to ten merk lands, the lands of <hi>Barr</hi> extending to nine merk lands, the land of easter and wester <hi>Balwillings</hi> extending to four merk lands, the lands of <hi>Drumoir</hi> extending to four merk lands, and the lands of <hi>Escan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numon</hi> extending to three merk lands, the lands of <hi>Escanelbeg</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to three merk lands, the lands of <hi>Lorsbeg</hi> extending to two merk lands, the lands of <hi>Basconal</hi> extending to three merk lands, the lands of <hi>Ballminoch</hi> over and nether extending to five merks land; the lands of <hi>Phenorbie</hi> and <hi>Clathline</hi> extending to eight merk lands: the lands of <hi>Pemyuaire</hi> and <hi>Alteriff,</hi> extending to four merks lands; the lands of <hi>Lagan</hi> extending to three merk lands; the lands of <hi>Drumgarno</hi> extending to four merk lands the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:176169:8"/>
               <hi>Corputiachen</hi> extending to four merk lands, of <hi>Clungarth</hi> extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to four merk lands: the Lands of <hi>Mergamumgath</hi> extending to four merk lands, the lands of <hi>Auchtertadour</hi> extending to two merks lands, the lands <hi>Glencardoch</hi> extending to two merks lands; the lands <hi>Belloch</hi> extending to three merk lands: the lands of <hi>Killmaluock</hi> extending to two merk lands; the lands of <hi>Annot</hi> extending to three merk and half merk lands; the lands of <hi>Garnald</hi> extending to two merk lands, the lands of <hi>Storocka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daill</hi> extending to two merk lands, the lands of <hi>Moyastil</hi> extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to five merk lands; the lands of <hi>Crobstil,</hi> extending to four merk lands, the lands of <hi>Broltes</hi> extending to five merk lands, the lands of <hi>Gortinweel</hi> extending to four merk lands; the lands of <hi>Grenan</hi> extending to two merk lands; the lands of <hi>Spensadge</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to two merk lands, the lands of <hi>Crosage</hi> extending to four merk lands, the lands of <hi>Balligregan</hi> and <hi>Mansreoch</hi> extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to three merk lands, the lands of <hi>Blair</hi> extending to one merk land, the lands of <hi>Donnonophine</hi> extending to two merk lands, the lands of <hi>Kildonan</hi> extending to two merk lands, the lands of <hi>Depen</hi> extending to three merk lands, the lands of <hi>Adquoadail</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to four merk lands, the lands of <hi>Auchnasale</hi> extending to two merk lands; the lands of <hi>Ranadail</hi> extending to four merk lands; the lands of <hi>Barwarcraig</hi> and <hi>Kirdinask</hi> extending to two merk lands, the lands of <hi>Killmichael</hi> extending to two merk lands, the lands of <hi>Stronoven</hi> extending to two merk lands, the lands of <hi>Auchmera</hi> extending to two merk lands, the lands of two <hi>Duchries</hi> extending to two merk lands. And likewise all and hail the lands and others underwritten of South <hi>Kintire,</hi> the lands of <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligregan</hi> and <hi>Cragack</hi> extending to four merk lands, the lands of <hi>Lossit</hi> and <hi>Glenhaughtie</hi> extending to five merk lands; the lands of <hi>Knockantmore</hi> extending to four merk eight shilling and four pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie lands, the lands of <hi>Drumtinul Lochoridail</hi> extending to four merk lands, of the other half of the saids lands extending to two merk lands, the lands of <hi>Teranois</hi> and <hi>Largaban</hi> extending to five merk lands, the lands of <hi>Glatechel</hi> extending to one merk lands, the lands of <hi>Machriemisso</hi> extending to one merk land, the lands of <hi>Darinachin</hi> extending to one merk lands, the lands of <hi>Lystra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chnie</hi> and <hi>Tralachnie</hi> extending to ten shilling land, the lands of <hi>Paobil</hi> and <hi>Jnnangowie</hi> extending to five shilling and ten pennies land, the lands of <hi>Killquhilmich</hi> extending to two merk lands, the lands of <hi>Blacknachouil</hi> extending to three merk lands, the lands of <hi>Kiluenine</hi> extending to seventeen merk lands, the lands of <hi>Wigil, Achurrich, Kilbride, Kinnachine, Ahnefleshim</hi> and <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teramaie</hi> extending to seven merk half merk lands, the lands of <hi>Knockreock, Morglenadul, Anhrerion</hi> extending to five merk and half merk lands, the lands of <hi>Knockreochbeg, Armacavish,</hi> and <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tobodouie</hi> extending to four merk lands; the lands of <hi>Kinloch</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to twelve merk lands, of <hi>Killdalick, Knockquhirk, Ach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>achon</hi> extending to four merk lands, the lands of <hi>Ballantyne, Auch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torve</hi> and <hi>Ballinabraid</hi> extending to six merk lands, the lands of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:176169:8"/>Machriemoir extending to twelve merk lands: the lands of Culder and Glenamuckloch extending to seven merk lands: the lands of Pulvilling extending to five merk half merk lands: the lands of Glenharvy extending to three merk lands: the lands of Gornogor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doch extending to one merk land: the land of Arradil extending to one merk land; the lands of Suckath extending to one merk land: the lands of Corfyne and Blairfairne extending to two merk lands: the lands of Craig extending to four merk lands: the lands of Cullilnewgirth extending to four merk lands. the lands of Kilmitchail and Achalick extending to four merk lands: the lands of Corslay extending to twelve merk lands: the lands of Mull and Kintyre extending to four merk lands: the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ds of Kermanoch and Mucklock extending to two merk lands: the lands of Collison, Forti, Ballivenan and Dallarnach extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to four merk eight shilling and four penny lands: the lands of Gartavach extending to one merk lands: the lands of Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chribeg extending to two merk lands: the lands of Leppenbeg extending to eight shilling four pennie lands: the lands of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrechastle extending to eight shilling four penny land: the lands of Kermmoir extending to twenty shilling lands: the lands of Glaicleffincarrar extending to two merk lands: the half of the lands of Lailt and Lippinstra extending the twenty six shilling eight penny land, of the lands of Cattadul, Laborgan, Garvine: the lands of Brakleid and Garkloftan extending to eight merk lands: the lands of Brownorichnie, Drumnarenoch, Barsomeal, Leynamse and Innaracaldoch extending to four merk two shilling and ten penny lands: the lands of Killiallane, Penniegownie, Gortoscane, Elderice, Ardnascavis extending to eight merk lands: the lands of Achnaglack, Lagnacraig, Kerimarnoch, Kerifour, Ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donal, Dungliss and Glenramskilmore, Scone and Glenadail extending to twelve merk lands: the lands of Kiulain extending to two merk lands: the lands of Culrathane, Dalnaleith, Chrish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolloch extending to four merk lands: the lands of Kilruane, Knockstake and Lenachane extending to three merk and half merk lands: the lands of Gortonougonriach extending to eight shilling four penny land: and all and hail the lands and Isle of Jura, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending the particular lands and others under-written. <hi>viz.</hi> the lands of Ardyne extending to sixteen shilling eight penny land: the lands of Stronyne extending to sixteen shilling eight penny land: the lands of Bowastle extending to sixteen shilling eight pennie land: the lands of Sandack extending to sixteen shilling eight penny land: the lands of Craigeib extending to sixteen shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling eight penny land: the lands of Knocknafollan extending to sixteen shilling eight penny land: the lands of Auchahorse ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to sixteen shilling eight penny land: the lands of Ny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryne extending to sixteen shilling eight penny land: the lands of Knockbrowane extending to sixteen shilling eight penny land: the lands of Ardirnel extending to sixteen shilling and eight pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny land: the lands of Knockbreck extending to eight shilling
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:176169:9"/>land, with all and sundry Isles, Castles, Towers, Fortalices, Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner places, houses, Biggings, Yards, Orch-yards, Milns, miln-lands, Multures, Woods, Fishings, Coals, Coal-heughs, Cunnings, Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninghairs, Doves, Dovecots, Tennents, Tennendries, Annexis, Connexis, Dependences, Forrests, Out-sets, parts, pendicles and pertinents whatsomever, of all and sundry the foresaids lands, Isles, and others above-written: all lyand within the said Sheriffdom of Tarbot of old, and now within the said Sheriffdom of Argile: and likewise all and sundry Feu-ferms, and others aftermention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, due to Us out of the lands above and under-written, <hi>viz.</hi> sixty six <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> Ferm, and twelve Bolls of Malt for the foresaid twelve merk lands of Auchricroce, ninety four <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> of Meal for the foresaids lands of Bar: an hundreth twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty six <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> of Meal, and sixty four bolls of Malt for the foresaid seventeen merk lands of Kildonald: six <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> of Meal for the foresaid four merk land of Craig: an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and eighty four <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> of Meal: sixty four bolls of Malt for the foresaid twelve merk lands of Carskoy: eighty two <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> of Meal for the foresaid five merk and half merk lands of Polwilling: ninety <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> of Meal, and ten bolls of Malt for the foresaid seven merk lands of Kildair and Glen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muckloch, an hundred eighty six <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> of Meal, and sixty four bolls of Malt for the foresaid twelve merk land of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriemoir, all lyand within the foresaid Lordship of Kintire, the saids feu Ferms extending in the whole to twenty Chalders of Corn, of which, six Chalders and ten bolls of Meal, and thret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Chalders six bolls of Malt: as also, all and hail the lands of Glendarwal: and all and hail the lands of Dounoone, with Castles, Towers, Fortalices, manner Places, Houses, Biggings, Yards, Orch-yards, Milns, Miln-lands, Multures, Woods, Fish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Tennents, Tennendries, annexis, connexis, Dependences, Forrests, Parts, Pendicles and Pertinents of the samine whatsom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, lyand within the foresaid Sheriffdom of <hi>Argile:</hi> and all and hail the lands and others under-written, <hi>viz.</hi> all and hail the six penny land of <hi>Auchibeg</hi> and <hi>Irnes:</hi> the two penny land of <hi>Culky<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyny:</hi> the four merk land of <hi>Auchiforsis:</hi> the three pound land of <hi>Auchnagowin:</hi> a penny land of <hi>Henbeg:</hi> a penny land of <hi>Adamgus:</hi> a penny land of <hi>Corasmindail:</hi> two penny and half penny lands of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> two penny and half penny lands of <hi>Corwayne</hi> extending to twelve merk lands, House, Biggings, Yards, Woods, Fishings, parts, pendicles and pertinents whatsomever of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saids lands, all lyand in <hi>Moir vairne,</hi> of old within the Sheriff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Inverness,</hi> and now within the Sheriffdom of <hi>Argile:</hi> and likewise, all and hail the Lands of <hi>Dounamuck</hi> and <hi>Auchnas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shalla,</hi> with Houses, Biggings, Yards, Parts, Pendicles, and all and sundry Pertinents of the samine whatsomever, lyand in <hi>Gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strie</hi> within the foresaid Sheriffdom of <hi>Argile:</hi> all and sundry the lands of <hi>Ferriland</hi> of <hi>Cardross,</hi> extending to four Aikers of land, with Houses, Biggings, Yards, Parts, Pendicles and Pertinents of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:176169:9"/>the samine whatsomever, with the Office of carrying in the Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry-boats of <hi>Cardross,</hi> with all and sundry Casualities thereof: Which also with the Pasturage of six Soums and an Horse Grass within the lands of <hi>Kicktoun</hi> of <hi>Cardross,</hi> with all and sundry Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the samine, lyand within the Lordship of <hi>Cardross</hi> and Sheriffdom of <hi>Dumbartoun:</hi> all and sundry the Lands of <hi>Finlay</hi> and <hi>Locker</hi>
               <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> comprehending the Lands and others under-written, <hi>viz.</hi> The Lands of <hi>Moy</hi> and <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> the Lands of <hi>Barinwailitan, Invermusk, Vullen, Auchnarrie, Auch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nannalla, Lochmalchri, Glenmaltre, Deurack, Invermalzie, Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, Kilrosse, Auchnacarie, Cluins, Invertoiwolg, Avchnasal, Tail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salauchan, Mockinmoir, Kennaught, Inurualagan, Kerlacht, Glen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deseroch, Glesbraega, Glenpean, Kinloch, Glenkinkie, Marserolish, Arcui</hi> with all and sundry Castles, Towers, Fortalices, manner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>places, House, Biggings Yards, Orch-yards, Milns, Miln-lands, Multures, Suckens and Sequels of the samine, Woods, Fishings, Salmond-fishings and other fishings, Forrests, Timber, Planting, Growing-trees, Muers, Marishes, Meadows, Tofts, Crofts, Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sets, insets, Grassings, Glening, Sheallings and universal Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinents thereof, lyand within the Lordship of <hi>Lochabar,</hi> and She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffdome of <hi>Inverness.</hi> And all and sundry the Lands and Barrony of <hi>Auehna garran,</hi> five pound land of old extent of <hi>Cragfurlinach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, Kaith, Balichindren, Les, Mckn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>one,</hi> the lands <hi>Couchrychan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nach; Stellag</hi> and <hi>Kildalvan;</hi> with Castles, Towres, Fortalices, Maner-places, Houses, Biggings, Yeards, Orchards; Milne Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Woods, Fishings, Lochs, Bogs, Tennents, Tennendries, Annexis, Connexis, Dependences, Parts, Pendicles and pertin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents thereof whatsomever, lyand within the Bailrie of <hi>Cowal</hi> and Shiriffdome of <hi>Argyle</hi> forsaid. All and sundry the Lands commonly called the over and nether <hi>Monies</hi> of <hi>Dollor.</hi> All and hail the Lands of <hi>Glencarne,</hi> lyand at the back of the water bank of <hi>Dollor,</hi> with all and sundrie, Houses, Biggings; Yeards, Milnes, multurs, Woods, Fishings, Parts, Pendicles and Pertients of the famine whatsomever, lyand within the Sheriffdom of <hi>Clackman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</hi> All and hail the Lands of <hi>Bank</hi> called bank of <hi>Dollor,</hi> and <hi>Orchards,</hi> and half Milne of <hi>Dollorbeg</hi> with Milnes, Milne-lands, Multurs, Sequells, Coals, Coal-heughs, Doves, Dovcats, and all and sundrie Pertinents of the famine whatsomever, and two quarter Sheriffdail <hi>Cinuarnniptibus</hi> Pendicles and Pertinents of the samin, lyand within the Regality of <hi>Drumfer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ling</hi> and Sheriffdom of <hi>Clackmanan</hi> forsaid. All and hail the Lands of <hi>Overkendder</hi> with Houses, Biggings, Yeard, Milnes. Multurs, Woods, Fishings, Coals, Coal-heughs, Doves, Dovcats, Tennents, Tennendries, Parts Pendicles and Pertinents of the samine whatsomever, lyand within the Sheriffdom of <hi>Fyfe</hi> forsaid. All and hail the two merk and ten shilling Land of <hi>Ballniab,</hi> The six shilling and eight pennie land of <hi>Arsit,</hi> the six shilling and eight pennie land of <hi>How,</hi> and half merk land of <hi>Saligo,</hi> with Houses, Biggings, Parts, Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicles and Pertinents of the samin whatsomever, lyand within the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:176169:10"/>Sheriffdom of <hi>Tarbat,</hi> and Isle of Isla foresaid, and now within the Sheriffdom of <hi>Argyle.</hi> All and Hail the sixteen shilling and eight pennie land of <hi>Cumnie</hi> in <hi>Jura,</hi> with Houses, Biggings, Yeards, Tofts, Crofts, Woods, Salmond-fiishings, and other Fish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, as well in fresh water as in salt, and Lochs, and Grassing, Pasturages, Parts, Pendicles, and Pertinents of the famine whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, with the Libertie of Forrestrie of the saids Lands and other, abovewritten lyand within the bounds of <hi>Tarbot</hi> of old, and now within the said Sheriffdom of <hi>Argyle.</hi> And all other Lands, Heritages, Teinds, Tenements, Annualrents and others whatsomever pertaining to the said late Earl of <hi>Argyle,</hi> wherever the saminlye within the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> of whatsomever Name, Title or Designation the samin be off, and contained in the said late Earl of <hi>Argyle</hi> his Infestments of the samin: Which are holden as exprest, designed and set down in the said Charter, whereanent We have dispensed for ever: Reserving out of the Lands abovespecified, disponed to the Trusties above-named, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as at the sight and determination of Our saids Commission<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of yearly Rent, as being joyned with the lands above-written, wherein <hi>Archibald Campbel</hi> late Lord <hi>Lorn</hi> stands confirmed, will amount to the sum of fifteen thousand pounds, to be disposed afterwards be Us at Our pleasure. And, We, for Our Self and Successors, have given, granted and disponed seven thousand merks of yearly Rent to be designed be Our said Commissoners, in favours of <hi>Anna</hi> late Countes of <hi>Argyle,</hi> frae the date of Our Signator, at Our Cout, at <hi>New-mercat,</hi> the seventeen day of <hi>March</hi> last by-past, and in time coming, during all the dayes of her Life-time. Which Earldoms, Lordships, Barronies, Tennendries and others re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spective, abovewritten, pertained of before to the said <hi>Archibald</hi> late late Earl of <hi>Argyle,</hi> and are now fallen and become in Our hands, by the Forfaulture forsaid. And sicklike, We, with advice and consent forsaid, be Our said Charter: Have assigned, transfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and disponed to the said Sir <hi>William Paterson,</hi> Sir <hi>Alexander Gibson</hi> and <hi>George Mckenzie,</hi> and failzeing of either of them be decease, to the surviver. All and sundrie Contracts, Bonds, Obligations, Dispositions, Charters, Precepts and Instruments of Seizings, Services, Retours, Procutries and Instruments of Resig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, Tacks and rights of Teinds, and other Writs and Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, Rights; Titles and Securities whatsomever: made and granted be whatsomever Person or Persons: to the said late Earl of <hi>Argyle,</hi> or any other his Predecessors: or to any other person or persons for their behove; directly or indirectly in any sort: toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Decreet and Sentence of Forefaulture: and all other sentences of that nature Pronounced, or to be Prounced against the said late Earl his Lands, or Estate in sua far as the samin may conduce to the saids Trusties their securitie, with all that his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, or may follow on the Premisses, for now and ever: And if any part of the Lands of the said late Earl of <hi>Argyle</hi> hold of any other immediate Supperiour. We, by Our said Chartor, have
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:176169:10"/>ordained Our Lords Commissioners of Our Thesaurie, and Our Lords of Exchequer, to grant Presentations to Our saids Trusties. Presenting them as Vassells to the saids immediat Supperiors in due and competent form. As also, We have ordained our saids Lords of Exchequer, to grant Gifts to the forsaids Trusties of the said late Earl of <hi>Argyle,</hi> his hail Goods, Gear, Debts, Sums of money, Bonds, Obligations, and Insight Plenishing pertaining to him, and now belonging to Us, as said is, to be past under Our Privy Seal as accords. The Debts respective above-disponed in favours of the Laird of <hi>Glengarie,</hi> and <hi>Donald M<seg rend="sup">c</seg>donald</hi> of <hi>Moydart</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nowayes comprehended therein. And farder We by Our said Charter, have decerned and ordained that an Seising to be taken thereupon be the saids Trusties in all time coming, at the Tower, Fortalice and Maner-place of <hi>Inverrara,</hi> or upon any part of the saids Lands, Earldoms, Lordships and Barronies be earth and stone, shall be ane valid and sufficient Seising, for all and sundrie Lands, Lordships, Barronies, Burghs of barronie, Milnes, Woods, Forrests, Teinds, Feu-duties, Casualities, Liberties and others <hi>respectivè</hi> abovewritten: With all and sundrie Castles, Towers, Fortalices, Maner-place, Houses, Biggings, Yeards, Orchards, Milnes, Woods, Meadows, Parts, Pendicles and others Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly above-specified. And for every part and portion of the samine, without any other particular Seising to be taken at any other part or place, notwithstanding of the diverse denominations of the saids Lands, Lordships, Barronies and othersforesaid. And notwithstanding that they lye discontiguous and in divers Sheriff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms: Which Seising, with all that may follow thereupon, We, for Us and Our Successors, by Our said Chartor; have dispens<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for ever to be holden be the said Trusties of Us, and Our Successors in Fie and Heritage, free Earldoms, Lordships and Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronie for ever; be all Rights and Marches of the samin. old and devised: as the samine lyes in length and breadth, in Houses; big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging. Mures, Marishes; <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Meadows; Pasturages; Peits; Turffs; Coalls; Coal-heughs; Cunnings: Cunningars <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Doves: Dovcats. Lyme: Lymstone: Halking Hunting: <hi>&amp;c.</hi> With Court: Plent: Herizald: Blood-wyts: <hi>&amp;c.</hi> With Fark: Fose: Sack: Sock: Thoil: Them: Wrack: Wair. Venison: <hi>&amp;c.</hi> outsang-thief: infang-Theif: Pitt and Gallows: free ish and entrie. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> With all and sundrie other Liberties: <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Friely Quietly: <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But any Revocation: Immpediment or Obstacle whatsomever: Givand therefore yearly the saids Trnsties to Us and Our Succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors for the forsaids Lands: Earldoms: Lordships: Barronies and others respective above-written: with the pertinents. The Feu and blensh Duties and other Duties: Rights and Services: if any be due forth of the samin: And performing all other Conditions: contained in the old Infestments thereof: for all other burden: question: demand or secular service which may be any ways ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or craved forth of the saids Lands: and others forsaids in time coming; And for the better compleating of the forsaid se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>several
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:176169:11"/>Rights, We, by Our said Charter have ordained, that the Lands, Jurisdictions, Offices, Supperiorities, Patrouages, Constabularies, and others above-written shal be Annexed to Our Crown in Our nixt Session of Parliament, or Parliament to be holden by Us. In which We promised, in <hi>verbo Princip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> to ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifle, and by Our said Chartor, We have commanded Our saids Estates of Parhament to ratifie accordingly, conform to the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saids Rights, and respective Interests abovespecefied. And last<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by Our said Charter, We have declared, that the foresaid Gift, in swa far as may be extended to the Lands, Earldomes, Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships, and others abovewritten, with the pertinents, is granted by Us to the said Sir <hi>William Paterson,</hi> Sir <hi>Alexander Gibson</hi> and <hi>George Mckenzie,</hi> upon Trust, for the use and behove of such as shal he found to be true and lawful Creditors to the late Marquess of <hi>Argyle,</hi> and the late Earl of <hi>Argyle</hi> his Son, in whose favours the saids confident Persons, by Our said Charter are oblidged to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nude themselves, and that how soon the respective parsells of the saids Lands shall be Allocated, Ordained and Appointed for the aids Creditors, by Our Commissioners afternamed: Which Ordinance, under Our Clerks hand of Our Commission under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written, with one Disposition from Our saids Trusties shal be an valid and sufficient Right and convoyance to the saids Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diters in all time coming. And to the end the saids Debts may be instructed, and all occasions granted in manner above-specified, We, by Our saids Charter, have given and granted full Power and Commission to Sir <hi>George Gordonn</hi> of <hi>Haddo,</hi> Lord Prese<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of Our Session, <hi>Robert</hi> Lord <hi>Nairn, Charles Maitland</hi> of <hi>Halt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Our Thesauter Depute, Sir <hi>George Mckenzie</hi> of <hi>Tarbat,</hi> Clerk to Our Registers and Rolls, Sir <hi>James Foules</hi> of <hi>Collingtoun,</hi> Sir <hi>David Nevoy</hi> of <hi>Nevoy,</hi> Sir <hi>John Lockhart</hi> of <hi>Castle-hill,</hi> Sir <hi>David <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of <hi>Forret,</hi> Sir <hi>James Foules</hi> of <hi>Reidfoord,</hi> Sir <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid Falconer</hi> of <hi>Nowtoun</hi> Sir <hi>Alexander Seatoun</hi> of <hi>Pitmedden,</hi> Sir <hi>Redger Hog</hi> of <hi>Harcas,</hi> Sir <hi>Andrew Birnie</hi> of <hi>Saline,</hi> Sir <hi>John M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ray</hi> of <hi>Drumsairn</hi> Sir <hi>Patrick Oglvie</hi> of <hi>Boyne:</hi> ordinary Lords to Our Counsell and Session. And to <hi>John</hi> Duke of <hi>Lauder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dail, John</hi> Marquess of <hi>Athol, William</hi> Marquess of <hi>Queensberry, Alexander</hi> Earl of <hi>Murray,</hi> extraordinary Lords of Our Session, and Lords of Our Privy Council, and their Successors, in Office for the time being, or any nine of them to conveen and meet within our Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> the first dyet being upon the twentie eight day of <hi>March</hi> last, and the other dyet to be with all convenient dilligence, for the hearing, and determining of all the Claimes and Interests of the Creditors of the said <hi>Archibeld</hi> late Earl of <hi>Argyle,</hi> and <hi>Archibald</hi> late Marquess of <hi>Argyle</hi> his said Father. And of the other Donators, and Persons having Interest in the Fortune and Estate of the said late Earle of <hi>Argyle,</hi> now fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len in Our hands by the forsaid Forefaulture. And for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter effectuating of the said design. We, by Our said Charter, have likewise granted sull Power and Commission to Our saids Lords,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:176169:11"/>to call before them all the Creditors of the said late Earl of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyle,</hi> or the late Marquess of <hi>Argyle</hi> his said Father, and all others having or pretending to have Interest in the Fortune and Estate Personal and Real of the said late Earl of <hi>Argyle</hi> upon such times and occasions as they should think fit; and for to emit and eshew forth Letters and Warrands for citing of the saids Creditors and others, at the head Burghs of the several Sheriffdoms within Our Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> upon twenty one dayes: And that for all such as are within this Our said Kingdom. And at the Mercat Cross of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Peir and Shoar of <hi>Leith</hi> upon threescore dayes, and that as to all such Persons as are without the Kingdom; declaring the said Citations to be a suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient warning to all the foresaids Persons, Creditors, and others concerned, as said is: With Certification to all who does not compear at their respective dyets, shall be for ever secluded from having any Claime or Interest in the forsaid Fortune and Estate of <hi>Argyle:</hi> with power likewise to Our saids Lords to prefer the foresaids Persons, Creditors and others, as they shall find just and right, having a speciall respect to such of the saids Creditors, who suffered for Us and Our Royal Fathers service, (And on that accompt) as also to make such inquiry, and take such probation anent the value of the said Fortune and Estate, as they shall find cause, and to divide the samine accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, not within Eighteen years purchase. And to determine all other contraversies that may arise thereanent: and general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all and every thing to do conform to the tennor of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laid Charter and Commission, as may best effectuat the samin And for the better compleating of the forsaids several Rights, We, by Our said Charter and Commission, have ordained, That the saids Jurisdictions, Offices, Superiorities, Patronages, Constabularies and others above-specified, shall be annexed to Our Crown, in Our first Session of Parliament, or Parliament holden by Us; in which, We, by Our said Charter and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission, have likewise promised in <hi>Verbo Principis</hi> to Ratifie and Confirm the forsaid several Rights, according to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spective Interests, above-specified. And We do by Our said Charter, Impower Our Lord Register to nominat a Clerk to the forsaid Commission; and who by vertue thereof, hes nominated Mr. <hi>Roderick Mckenzie</hi> Clerk to Our Session to be Clerk thereto, and ordained Our saids Commissioners to take the said Clerk his Oath <hi>de fideli administratione.</hi> And this Our present Commission to endure and continue untill the twenty eight day of <hi>March,</hi> one thousand six hundred and eighty seven years: and by Our said Charter, it is thereby declared, that the Syse of the Herring Fishing, within the hail Isles, Lochs and others above-written, Is no wayes comprehended in Our said Charter, but excepted therefrae, and left to be Disposed of at Our Pleasure, as the said Charter under Our Great Seal, of the Date above written, amply proports: In obedience whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:176169:12"/>Our saids Lords impowered and Commissionate to the effect above-specified; Having upon the foresaid first day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for meeting by the foresaid Commission; and at several other Dayes thereafter; and last upon the Day and Date of thir Presents Met, and having considered the foresaid Charter and Commission, and being therewith well and rypely advised, they Ordained thir Our Letters to be Direct at the instance of Our Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vits Sir <hi>George Mckenzie</hi> of <hi>Rosebaugh,</hi> Our Advocate for Our Interest: and also at the Instance of the said Sir <hi>Alexander Gibson,</hi> Sir <hi>William Paterson</hi> and <hi>George Mckenzie,</hi> as Trusties by the Foresaid Charter, for, and in Name and behalf of Our Donators, the Children, Creditors and others of the Family of <hi>Argile,</hi> for Summonding of all the Creditors of the said <hi>Archibald</hi> late Earl of <hi>Argile</hi> and the late Marquess of <hi>Argile,</hi> his said Father, and all Vassals and others having, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to have interest to the Lordships, Baronies and others contained in the said late Earl of <hi>Argile</hi> his Charter; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the foresaid Charter granted by Us in favours of the Trusties; and of any other Estate Personal or Real, which did belong to the said late Earl, at the Mercat Cross of the head Burghs of the several Sheriffdoms within Our Kingdom of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to compear before Our saids Lords of Council and Session, Commissioners foresaid, upon twenty one dayes after publication of thir Our Letters, and that as to all Persons within Our said Kingdom; and at the Mercat Cross of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Peer and Shore of <hi>Leith</hi> upon threescore Dayes; and that as to all persons without Our Kingdom, and that they bring with them their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spective Clames, Grounds, Instructions and Verificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thereof: And all Rights and Evidents of, and concerning the foresaids Lands, Teinds and others, and give in the samine to the said Mr. <hi>Roderick Mckenzie,</hi> Clerk appointed for this Commission, betwixt the twenty Day of <hi>July</hi> next to come, and eight Day of <hi>August</hi> thereafter, with Continuation of Dayes, With certification to such of the saids Creditors that does not compear and give in their Clames, Crounds and Instructions thereof, and produce, <hi>ut supra,</hi> shall never be heard thereafter to clame any share of the Benefite and Favour intended by Us: Nor the Vassals, or others to quarrel or impugne the Sentence, Allocating, Distributing and Dividing the saids Lands and others foresaids, upon pretence of any Right or interest they have, or may clame in, or concerning the samine: And Ordains the saids Persons, Creditors and others to attend such other Dayes and Dyets, as Our saids Lords shall appoint to give their Oathes anent the verity of their refpective Debts, if the samine shall be required: As likewise, Our saids Lords Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dains thir Our Letters, likewise to be direct at the foresaids Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, their Instances, for Summoning of such Persons, as they will make use of as Witnesses for proving of the Rental; and for Exhibiting in the hands of Our said Clerk of the Rental Books, Tacks, or any others Writs which may clear the just Rent and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:176169:12"/>Value of the said Estate, personal and real, which did belong to the said late Earl of <hi>Argile,</hi> to compear before Our saids Lords upon the saids twenty Day of <hi>July</hi> next, and eight Day of <hi>August</hi> thereafter, with Continuation of Dayes, with Certifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the saids Witnesses and others, the havers of the Rental Books, Tacks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as an Act made by Our saids Lords, of the date of their Presents; Ordaining thir Our Letters, and Executo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials to be direct in manner, to the effect, and with Cerrificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in manner above and after exprest at more length bears. Our Will is herefore, and We Charge you straitly and Commands, that incontinent thir Our Letters seen, ye pass to the Mercat Cross of the head Burghs of the several Sheriffdomes within this Our Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and there at each several Cross, Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Warn and Charge, all the Creditors of the said <hi>Archibald</hi> late Earl of <hi>Argile,</hi> and the late Marquess of <hi>Argile</hi> his said Father, and all Vassals and others having, or pretending to have Interest to the Lordships, Baronies and others contained in the said late Earl of <hi>Argile</hi> his Charter, and repeated in the foresaid Charter granted by Us, in Favours of the foresaid Trusties, and of any other Estate personal or real, which did belong to the said late Earl, to compear before Our saids Lords of Council and Session-Commissioners foresaid, upon twenty one Dayes, after publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of thir Our Letters, and that as to all persons within Our said Kingdom, and at the Mercat Cross of <hi>Edinburgh, Peer</hi> and Shore of <hi>Leith,</hi> upon threescore Dayes, and that as to all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons without Our Kingdom, and that they bring with them their respective Clames, Grounds, Instructions, and Verifications thereof; and all Rights and Evidents of, and concerning the foresaids Lands, Teinds and others, and give in the samine to the said Mr. <hi>Roderick Mckenzie,</hi> Clerk fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, appointed for this Commission, betwixt and the saids twenty Day of <hi>July</hi> next to come, and eight Day of <hi>August</hi> next thereafter, with continuation of Dayes, with Certificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to such of the saids Creditors that does not compear, and give in their Clames, Grounds and Instructions thereof, and produce <hi>ut supra,</hi> shall never be heard thereafter to clame any share of the Benefite and Favour intended by Us, nor the Vassals and others to quarrel and impugne the Sentence, Allocating, Distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting and Dividing the saids Lands and others foresaids, upon pretence of any Right or Interest they have, or may claim in, or concerning the famine: And Ordains the saids Persons, Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors and others to attend such other Dayes and Dyets as Our saids Lords shall appoint to give their Oaths anent the Verity of the their respective Debts, if the samine shall be required: As likewise, We Command and Charge you, that incontinent, thir Our Letters seen, ye pass, and in Our Name and Authority, Summond, Warn and Charge the Persons following, To wit,</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:176169:13"/>
            <p> To compear before Our saids Lords of Council and Session, the saids twenty Day of the said Month of <hi>July</hi> next to come, and eight Day of <hi>August</hi> next thereafter, with continuation of Days, to exhibite and produce in the hands of the said Mr. <hi>Roderick Mckenzie,</hi> the Rental Books and Tacks, or any other Writs which may clear the just Rent and Value of the foresaid Estate, personal and real, which did belong to the said late Earl of <hi>Argile:</hi> As also to Give and Declare their Oaths of Verity, in swa far as they know, or shall be speired at them, for clearing of the just Rent and Value of the foresaid Estate, with Certification to the saids Witnesses, or other Persons, havers of the foresaid Rental Books, Tacks and others, if they failzie to compear to the effect foresaid, Our other Letters of Caption shall be direct, Charging them <hi>simpliciter</hi> thereto, according to Justice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as ye will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to Us thereupon. The which to Do, We commit to you, conjunctly and severally, Our full Power, by thir Our Letters, delivering them back again by you, duely execute and indorsed again to the bearer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Given under Our Signet at</hi> Edinburgh, <hi>the twenty day of</hi> May, <hi>One thousand six hundred eighty two, and of Our Raign, the thretty and fourth year.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Per actum Dominornm Commissionariorum. Sic Subscribitur,</hi> RO. MACKENZIE.</signed>
               <dateline>Signet <date>
                     <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> 1682.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <closer>GOD save the KING.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:176169:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>